Last November, the Oscars Oldest Living Academy
Award winner and Oregon resident James Elmer
Williams passed away.
Here to share some of the 102-year-old's
incredible history and movie memorabilia,
we welcome back antique
appraiser Gary Germer.
Good to see you, Gary.
You too, Ellen.
Tell me about this man.
Well, Elmer Williams, he was known as, he's not
necessarily on the tip of everyone's tongue,
but he was more behind the scenes.
He won an Oscar for film editing
in 52 for the movie High Noon.
High Noon, yeah.
He was nominated two other times, but
he was also a producer, a director.
He was the head of Fox Studios
in Europe for a lot of years.
Oh, wow.
He worked on the movie The Longest Day, I don't
know if you remember, with Robert Meechum,
which was World War II.
The early Private Ryan.
Right.
There you go.
That's incredible.
And, you know, I got a chance to hold
this Oscar, and I have to say, it's heavy.
Yeah.
It's very heavy.
It surprised me, too.
This is his actual Oscar.
Now, it's being donated to
the University of Michigan.
He has a movie of New Mexico film school,
along with the bulk of his library,
and it's his movie memorabilia library.
But we're dealing with
the rest of the estate.
Because you can't auction
off, you can't sell an Oscar.
They really, I mean, I don't think that
they can prosecute you, but that's really,
you'll be frowned on if you do.
Yes, exactly.
All right, let's talk
about some of the items.
Let's talk about this picture here.
Tell me about this.
Well, both these pictures, they're in the
business known as, they were title boards.
Title boards.
So the one on the end, he was a
producer of all the Ernest removals.
Remember those?
And that is a title board
from Ernest Goes to Jail.
And then one of his other movies he did was this
one here was called Those Magnificent Men and
Their Flying Machines.
Oh, wow.
And that's one of the title boards.
And these have become, as far as, the
originals normally were thrown away,
you know, after they used them.
They didn't want them.
But now, or the people would
keep them as souvenirs.
Right.
So they become extremely collectible.
People, there's a whole genre of people
who want this and related to movies.
Oh, my gosh.
It would be incredible to have.
Okay, so in front of the
Oscar, tell me about this.
I'm not sure if they can,
hopefully they can pick it up.
This is a box, a silver box that was given to
him for his production and directing of the movie
20,000 Leagues Under the Sea.
Which, as all of us, well, me
as a kid, I'm older than you.
It's a gift?
It was a gift.
It's him being the producer of
20,000 Leagues Under the Sea.
So that was a little cigarette box.
A cigarette box.
That's what I was wondering.
Okay, I was wondering what it was.
All right.
So it's interesting stuff.
He made it.
He made a movie called Caravan in Europe.
And that's what some of these
things are from, the fabrics.
And he also collected things.
The fabrics and the jewelry and
the gun, it's called a trade gun.
This gun?
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
It started in Europe in the
1600s, 1700s as a flintlock.
And then they would trade, you know, as weapons
got better in the West to the Middle East.
We kind of do the same thing today.
But they would embellish them.
They would take what was a normal
flintlock and embellish them.
It's from the movie Caravan, along with the antique
tribal jewelry from Afghanistan and Turkoman.
This is really, you'll see a lot of
like the belly dancing type jewelry.
Oh, this is, so I'm sorry.
This is really the fine,
yeah, it can't hurt anything.
But you can see that it's made of
silver and gold and carnelians.
Is this like a necklace or is this like a?
Yeah, this would have been worn
around, kind of just draped on.
Okay, that's incredible.
Those are fun, fun things.
And hard to find the really.
Great old antique pieces
from that part of the world.
The Turkoman or Turkman
people is what that's from.
They're tribal nomadic people.
Wow.
Now this piece is, I
don't know, incredible.
I've never seen anything like it before.
Tell me about that.
Well, this is, I brought this.
It wasn't actually in a movie,
but it was part of his collection.
And it's the single coolest
thing I've ever had.
Yeah, I've never seen
anything like this before.
It's an armor's model, an armor maker's model
from the late 1400s from northern Germany.
And I evidently would go.
I would go in and get
fitted for your armor.
And he would talk about the different parts
of the armor and how you wanted yours done.
And so it survived.
He collected some antiquities when
he was in Europe such as this.
We have an authentication from the British Royal
Museum of its age and authenticity with that.
Wow.
The crosses and the religious
items date back to the 5th century.
And are fun.
I mean, it's just really interesting
to see these things would last.
Now, you'd think something, this
is so unusual to have it complete.
Yeah.
So it's values by $10,000 to $15,000.
The other ones, actually,
more of those things survive.
So you're actually in the $300
to $400, $500 range on those.
Really?
Yeah.
So we can fix you up if you
want a 5th century cross.
Yeah.
I like those.
I find those really fascinating.
And lastly, just tell us
a little bit about these.
These are more current.
This was his wife's collection.
And she has 300 pieces of
what's known as Majolica.
And when they were in
Europe, she collected it.
The English-American.
And French made it.
And it's a heavy tin glaze from the 1900s.
I brought it.
I think it's just really
whimsical and colorful.
Yeah.
I've never seen anything like that.
Is that a picture of the parrot?
Is that a parrot, a picture?
Yeah.
He's an actual picture.
Wow.
Yeah.
And then you think of Victorian,
because he's like 1850s to 1900.
Right.
You think of Victorian as being
dark and heavy and gloomy.
Right.
Not so.
But really, no.
They were big on bright colors
and whimsical, fun things.
Wow.
Gary, thank you.
And thank you for introducing us to him.
That's fascinating.
And thanks for letting me hold you.
Hold the Oscar.
Yes.
I want to thank all the little people.